Guide to the New York University Department of History Oral History Class Collection OH.033
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I. Lower East Side Oral History Project Interviews, 1991-1994; 7 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 4 media boxes, and 8 card catalog drawers; 0.75 Linear Feet in one record carton; 4 videocassettes (hi8); 4 videodiscs (dvd); 192 sound discs (cd); 133 audiocassettes
  - Coffey, Jennie Wertheimer, 1993 May 26; 478416 (Box 1, Folder 21, Box 13, Cassette 49, Box 4, Cd 20)
    This interview was conducted by Helen Goodman on May 26, 1993 at Jennie Wertheimer Coffey's apartment in Brooklyn, New York. The interview covers Coffey's childhood in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Coffey recalls the apartment in which her family lived, including the layout and the fact that the family shared a bathroom with their neighbors. She recalls home remedies her mother used to treat colds and headaches. Coffey recounts moving to the Whitestone neighborhood of Queens with her husband and their children.
    Duration: 36:12
  - Dagstine, Beatrice "Betty", 1991 October 11; 478393 (Box 3, Cd 34, Box 12, Cassette 23, Box 1, Folder 22)
    Beatrice "Betty" Dagstine was born in the 1920s in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her father immigrated to the United States (US) from Austria and her mother immigrated to the US from Russia. Her father worked as a truck driver in the US. The family moved to different apartments on Cherry Street, Louis Street, and Broome Street in the LES. She attended Public School 147 (P.S. 147) and Seward Park High School in the LES. Dagstine married and was widowed soon after her marriage. She worked as a waitress. At the time of the interview, Dagstine had been a resident of the Vladeck Houses in the LES for 48 years and was the current president of The Women, a women's club at the Henry Street Settlement in the LES.
    This interview was conducted on October 11, 1991 by Elizabeth Nichols at the Henry Street Home Planning Workshop in the Vladeck Houses in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The majority of the interview covers Beatrice "Betty" Dagstine's enjoyment of living in the Vladeck Houses. Dagstine recalls living in a tenement building in the LES with her parents, where the bathtub was in the kitchen and the shared toilet was out in the hallway. She remembers playing kick the can with neighbors when she was child. She recalls the LES neighborhood as being safe and she said she rarely locked her apartment doors. Dagstine describes structure of The Women, a women's club at the Henry Street Settlement in the LES, including the dues structure, the meeting schedule, and the fact that it was a social club offered by the Henry Street Settlement.
    Duration: 47:26
  - DeAngelo, Rose Picca and Sam DeAngelo, 1992 November 17; 478376 (Box 1, Folder 23, Box 11, Cassette 2A-2B, Box 3, Cd 2-3)
    Rose Picca DeAngelo was born in 1915 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her parents immigrated to the United States from Milan, Italy in 1912. Her father worked as a construction worker and her mother worked as an office cleaner. DeAngelo was one of 15 children, eight of whom survived infancy. She attended the Transfiguration School in the LES. She married Sam DeAngelo in 1932 and had one son. Her husband attended Public School 23 in the LES and Haaren High School in Manhattan. He worked as a construction worker and coal tender before and during World War II, and as a bartender for 40 years. She worked in an unspecified hat factory, at the American Steel Wool Manufacturing Company factory, as a tomato packer, and as a seamstress at Post Manufacturing Company on Lafayette Street for 20 years. She was a member of an unspecified labor union (likely the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America).
    This interview was conducted on November 17, 1992 by Sushan Chin at Rose Picca DeAngelo's apartment in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. DeAngelo's husband, Sam DeAngelo, participates in the first half of the interview. The interview covers Rose DeAngelo's family and working life. DeAngelo discusses her childhood, including the apartments in which her family lived and the fact that her mother had 15 children. She discusses the death of seven of her siblings as infants, causes of infant mortality in the early 20th century, and the death of her father. She describes her siblings, their careers, and their families. DeAngelo and her husband recount their wedding and their 50th and 60th anniversary celebrations. Sam DeAngelo discusses discipline in school and at home, his working life, and his and Rose's reasons for staying in the LES. Rose DeAngelo discusses different jobs she had in an unspecified hat factory, at the American Steel Wool Manufacturing Company factory, as a tomato packer at an unspecified factory, and as a seamstress in an unspecified garment factory in the LES. She explains that she and her friend were strike breakers in the hat factory and her opinions of labor unions before and after this experience. She discusses the custom of having midwives attend at home births, her mother's four sets of twins, and their mortality rate. DeAngelo describes her work as a seamstress at Post Manufacturing Company on Lafayette Street, including the types of athletic clothes she made, the decline of the business, and working conditions in the factory. She describes the apartments in which she lived in the LES and sections of the neighborhood, including Worth Street and Mulberry Street Park. Other topics include military service of DeAngelo's family members, crime in the LES in the 1910s and at the time of the interview, Italian residents of the LES, and benefits of her membership in an unspecified labor union (likely the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America).
    Duration: 2:37:12
  - Dehar, Albert, 1993 May 22; 478411 (Box 12, Cassette 44, Box 4, Cd 14)
    Albert Dehar was born into a Turkish Jewish family in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Dehar was the eldest of five children. The family lived in a three room apartment on Orchard Street, in which Dehar lived until he was 18 years old. Dehar was active in the community and was a member of the Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union and a member of Local 65 of an unspecified labor union. He was drafted into the United States military during World War II.
    This interview was conducted on May 22 of an unspecified year by an unspecified interviewer at an unspecified location. The majority of the interview covers Albert Dehar's early life in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Dehar discusses living at his family's apartment at 139 Orchard Street and using the public baths located on Allen Street for their weekly Friday baths. He recalls attending an all boys elementary school, Public School 20 (P.S. 20), and playing stickball with his classmates and neighbors. Dehar describes his first paid job delivering apples and candies to office buildings on Wall Street with a pushcart and a later job as an errand boy for the button company B. Blumenthal & Co, where he participated in union activities.
    Duration: 01:06:76
  - Dell, Allen, 1994 April 10; 478464 (Box 14, Cassette 97, Box 1, Folder 24, Box 5, Cd 36)
    Allen Dell was born into a Jewish family in 1947 in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York on 4th Street and Avenue A. Dell's parents were born in the Lower East Side. All of Dell's grandparents immigrated to the United States from Russia. In 1952, Dell's family moved into a two bedroom apartment in a cooperative building on Grand Street. His father owned a restaurant and bar called Club 28 in the East Village neighborhood of Manhattan. At 10 years old, Dell got his first job at a butcher shop on Grand Street. Dell earned two master's degrees in music and special education and worked as a teacher for several years. In 1988, Dell's father purchased Katz's Delicatessen on East Houston Street.
    This interview was conducted on April 10, 1994 by Karen Baker at Katz's Delicatessen at 205 East Houston Street, Manhattan, New York. The interview is difficult to hear, due to a lot of background noise. The majority of the interview covers Dell's childhood experiences growing up in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan and owning Katz's Delicatessen. Dell explains the rules of box baseball, stickball, punchball, kick the can, and marbles. He recalls having to pause in the middle of stickball games to allow cars to drive past the game. Dell describes why Katz's Delicatessen is popular, stating his belief that maintaining their same means of operation, menu, location, and food preparation have all attributed to the delicatessen's continual success.
    Duration: 37:17.
  - Deutsch, Shirley Katz, 1993 July 26; 478417 (Box 1, Folder 25, Box 13, Cassette 50, Box 4, Cd 21)
    Shirley Katz Deutsch was born in 1923 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she had one sister. Her parents immigrated to the United States from Austria. Her father worked as a salesman and her mother managed the household. Deutsch attended Public School 110, Junior High School 12 and Seward Park High School in the LES. She worked as a secretary and as an aide in an elementary school. She was a member of the United Federation of Teachers. She married and had children.
    This interview was conducted on July 26, 1993 by Helen Goodman at Shirley Katz Deutsch's home in Brooklyn, New York. The interview covers Deutsch's early life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and her family. Deutsch describes the apartment in which her family lived on Cannon Street in the LES, the family's living arrangements, and their neighbors. She discusses the family's customs surrounding the Jewish holidays, including games she would play and food her mother would make. She recalls attending classes and events at the Clark House and the Grand Street Settlement in the LES. She recalls family members visiting her family's apartment. She discusses belonging to the Downtown Talmud Torah and participating in clubs and classes in the Educational Alliance in LES. She recounts her father's responsibilities as a cohen in a synagogue. Other topics include stores in her neighborhood, performers she saw at the Yiddish theatre, her religious upbringing, and her extended family.
    Duration: 34:44
  - Dick, Nellie, 1993 February 27; 478479 (Box 1, Folder 26, Box 15, Cassette 112A-112B, Box 6, Cd 13-14)
    Nellie Dick was born in 1893 to a Jewish family in Ukraine, Russia. In 1894, Dick's parents immigrated to England and settled in London. Her parents were members of anarchist groups and attended lectures given by Johann Rudolf Rocker. Dick attended classes at the Jubilee Street Club in London. In 1917, her family immigrated to the United States and settled in New York, New York. Dick married and moved with her husband to the anarchist community, the Ferrer Colony (also known as the Stelton Colony) in Stelton, New Jersey. Dick was a principal at the Colony's Modern School.
    This interview was conducted on February 27, 1993 by Christine Halvorson at Nellie Dick's house in Oyster Bay, New York. The interview is primarily with Nellie Dick and her son, Jim Dick, occasionally participates. The majority of the interview covers Nellie Dick's recollections of anarchist communities in London, England; New York; and New Jersey. Dick recalls attending a lecture given by Johann Rudolf Rocker in London when she was eight or nine years old and being the only child present at the lecture. She explains that her immersion into politics at a young age resulted in her dedicated involvement in the anarchist community. Dick goes into detail about what she considers to be the fundamental differences between anarchists and Communists, one being the belief that there should be a bit of a hierarchy to the working and social structure of a community. She describes teaching herself to read Yiddish and her eagerness to learn. Dick recalls working closely with her fellow principals at the Modern School to write the Voice of the Children, a Stelton Colony publication. As leaders of the Ferrer Colony, Nellie and her husband each proposed and carried out projects to better the community, including better living conditions for the boarding school students and improvements to school buildings. She explains that not only did the students attend classes at the school, they were also responsible for maintaining the grounds of the school. Dick describes teaching her students manners as she strongly believed in etiquette and discipline. Dick expresses her adoration for the Stelton Colony and her pride as a contributing leader of that community, as she was a proponent of always improving the community. She also explains the colony's mission, which expresses the importance of responsibility in order to have freedom, and the living atmosphere of the Ferrer Colony. Dick explains that she knew she belonged within the Ferrer Colony because she shared the outstanding belief that there should be a change in government and that all individuals should receive an education.
    Duration: 2:32:54
    Women and anarchism -- United States.; Ferrer Colony (Stelton, N.J.)
  - Dornfest, Shirley Rosenbaum, 1993 July 30; 478418 (Box 1, Folder 27, Box 13, Cassette 51, Box 4, Cd 22)
    Shirley Rosenbaum Dornfest was born in 1922 in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she had one brother. When she was nine years old, her family moved to the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan. Her father immigrated to the United States (US) from Poland and worked as a milliner. He died when Dornfest was 14 years old. Her mother immigrated to the US from Russia and worked as a seamstress. After the death of her father, Dornfest moved with her mother and brother to Brooklyn. Dornfest attended Seward Park High School in the LES, Brooklyn College in Brooklyn, and worked as a teacher. She was a member of the Workmen's Circle, Branch 1076 and participated in programs at the University Settlement and Educational Alliance in the LES.
    This interview was conducted on July 30, 1993 by Goldie Gold in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Shirley Rosenbaum Dornfest's early life and family. Dornfest discusses her family's apartments in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, on Eldridge and Clinton Streets. She describes both apartments, the living arrangements, and the ways in which the family members negotiated privacy for themselves. She describes the University Settlement in the LES and programs in which she participated there. She recounts games she and friends would play in the street. She discusses her father's work as a milliner before the Great Depression and as a salesman and barber during and after the Depression. She discusses his background, including his education and early life in Poland, his decision to immigrate to the US, his participation in pinochle and chess clubs in the LES, and his death when she was 14 years old. She recounts her mother's decision to work as a seamstress in order to supplement the family's income. She discusses her mother's background, including her family in Russia and the immigration pattern of her father and siblings. Dornfest discusses a social club she and her friends organized, named Club Yremus, including the friends who belonged to the club and the activities in which the group participated. Other topics include Dornfest's education, family members who lived in Palestine, and her brother.
    Duration: 1:29:12
  - Eisner, Esther Lorber, 1993 May 10; 478419 (Box 1, Folder 28, Box 13, Cassette 52, Box 4, Cd 23)
    Esther Lorber Eisner was born in 1906 in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she had two sisters. Her father immigrated to the United States (US) from Galicia in 1901 and her mother immigrated to the US from Poland in 1901. Her father worked as a peddler and her mother managed the household. Eisner attended Washington Irving High School in Manhattan. She worked as a bookkeeper. She married in 1927 and she and her husband lived in Brooklyn.
    This interview was conducted on May 10, 1993 by Helen Goodman at Esther Lorber Eisner's home in the Sheepshead Bay neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. The interview covers Eisner's early life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan and her family. Eisner describes the apartments in which her family lived in the LES, in particular their apartment on Goerck Street. She discusses her family's traditions around the Jewish sabbath, including having a non-Jewish person conduct chores for them during the sabbath and the foods her family would eat. She recounts using public bathhouses and discusses the family's neighbors and neighborhood traditions surrounding Jewish holidays and funerals. She discusses her education, including attending the Downtown Talmud Torah in the LES and Washington Irving High School in Manhattan. She discusses her family, including her parents' relationship with her mother's widowed sister and the fact that her husband did not want her to work outside of the home. She recalls speaking only Yiddish in the home until she attended school, at which time she and her sisters spoke English amongst themselves.
    Duration: 58:53
  - Epstein, Rebecca, 1992 November 15; 478377 (Box 1, Folder 29, Box 11, Video 3A-3C, Box 3, Dvd 4-6)
    Rebecca Epstein was born on October 17, 1898 in Boston, Massachusetts. At six years of age her family moved to the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her father immigrated to the United States from the Bessarabia region of Russia. Her family was Jewish.
    This interview was conducted on November 15, 1992 by Helen Selsdon and Sushan Chin at an unspecified location. Rebecca Epstein discusses the fact that her teachers in New York loved her Boston accent while her classmates derided it. She describes the layout and furnishing of her family's railroad apartment in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and discusses her family's practice of taking on boarders who were recent immigrants. She describes immigrants entering the United States through Castle Garden in Manhattan. Epstein discusses the deaths of three of her siblings, two of whom died from infantile cholera, or summer complaint. Epstein discusses her relationship with her father, in particular his attitude of superiority towards her mother and how his perceived hypocrisy led to Epstein's decision to become an atheist. Epstein also discusses childhood activities for earning money such as completing piecework and charging admission for plays organized by neighborhood children.
    Duration: 1:07:44
  - Feldman, Helen Levy, 1993 April 29; 478420 (Box 13, Cassette 53, Box 1, Folder 30, Box 4, Cd 24)
    Helen Levy Feldman was born in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York to an Orthodox Jewish family. Her father immigrated to the United States from Russia and her mother from Poland. Feldman had a stepsister and a brother. She participated in neighborhood institutions including the Educational Alliance, Madison House, and the Henry Street Settlement.
    This interview was conducted by Goldie Gold on April 29, 1993 at an unspecified location. The interview is primarily in English, with some Yiddish. Feldman discusses the difficulties her parents had adjusting to life in the United States, including poverty and raising a child with disabilities. Feldman discusses the shared class experience of people who lived in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She describes sharing bathrooms and throwing trash out of windows as typical for the neighborhood during her youth. Feldman discusses the importance of education for upward mobility and neighborhood organizations such as Workmen's Circle, Educational Alliance, Madison House, and Henry Street Settlement. She discusses peers that have moved away from the LES and how the neighborhood has changed.
    Duration: 1:09:07
  - Feuerman, Minnie Hoffinger, 1993 June 23; 478421 (Box 13, Cassette 54, Box 1, Folder 31, Box 4, Cd 25)
    Minnie Hoffinger Feuerman was born in 1909 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She lived in several apartments at 21-23 Avenue C in the LES before moving to the Borough Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. Her family was Jewish, and her parents immigrated to the United States from Poland. She attended Washington Irving High School in Manhattan, and married in 1926 at age 17. She worked for a year as a clerical worker at the National Biscuit Company. After her marriage she raised children and managed the household.
    This interview was conducted on June 13, 1993 by Helen Goodman at an unspecified location. Minnie Hoffinger Feuerman describes living conditions in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and the assistance that her family gave to other immigrants. She describes her parents taking on recent immigrants as boarders. She discusses Jewish traditions, including the sukkah. She discusses her parents' role in the Progressive Samborer Young Men's Benevolent Association, a charity that raised funds and performed traditional burial rights for Jewish immigrants. She discusses Jewish theater, including the custom of politicians giving away theater tickets during election season.
    Duration: 1:06:32
  - Fier, Ida, 1994 March 6; 478465 (Box 14, Cassette 98, Box 5, Cd 37-38, Box 1, Folder 32)
    Ida Fier was born in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York in 1924 to an Orthodox Jewish family. Her father, who emigrated from Austria-Hungary, had a rabbinical degree and died when Fier was eight years old. Her mother emigrated from Russia in 1900 because of pogroms. At 16, Fier was accepted to Brooklyn College and received a bachelor of arts in Political Science. Fier lived in the LES until her marriage.
    This interview was conducted on March 6, 1994 by Dawn Vander Vloed at an unspecified location. Ida Fier describes her childhood and adolescence in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She describes witnessing her father's death of a heart attack and her embarrassment at her mother's subsequent decision to become the janitor at their 232 Rivington Street apartment. Fier discusses her relationship with her mother, in particular her support of Fier's desire to attend college and their conflict over Orthodox Judaism. She describes feeling unable to discuss abortion and menstruation with her mother. Fier describes the importance of local institutions such as the Henry Street Settlement and the local library for entertainment and education. She describes doing schoolwork at the public library when there were guests at home, going to school during the summer to learn basket and rug weaving, and taking piano lessons at the Henry Street Settlement. She discusses the limited enforcement of quarantines in the LES. Fier discusses joining the Communist Party of the United States of America in college and being a student teacher at Seward Park High School. Fier discusses the impact of nostalgia on accounts of the LES by her generation, arguing that people are sentimental about their youths because their lives had more potential.
    Duration: 1:33:51
  - Flynn, Deborah Borgenicht, 1992 October 24; 478378 (Box 1, Folder 33, Box 3, Cd 7-8, Box 11, Cassette 4A-4B)